<?xml version = '1.0' encoding='US-ASCII'?>
<!DOCTYPE rfc SYSTEM "../xml2rfc-1.36/rfc2629.dtd" [
  <!ENTITY rfc2119     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2119.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2311     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2311.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2312     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2312.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2313     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2313.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2314     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2314.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2315     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2315.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2630     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2630.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2631     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2631.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2632     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2632.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2633     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2633.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2634     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2634.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc2985     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.2985.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3114     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3114.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3279     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3279.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3447     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3447.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3850     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3850.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3851     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3851.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc3852     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.3852.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc4055     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4055.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc4056     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.4056.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5035     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5035.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5280     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5280.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5652     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5652.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5750     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5750.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5751     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5751.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5755     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5755.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5758     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.5758.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc6090     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6090.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc6151     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6151.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc6194     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6194.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc6979     SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml/reference.RFC.6979.xml">
  <!ENTITY rfc5751bis  SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lamps-rfc5751-bis.xml">
  <!ENTITY eaiAddress  SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-lamps-eai-addresses.xml">
  <!ENTITY curdlePkix  SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.ietf-curdle-pkix.xml">
  <!ENTITY eddsa  SYSTEM "http://xml.resource.org/public/rfc/bibxml3/reference.I-D.irtf-cfrg-eddsa.xml">

]>

<?rfc toc='yes'?>
<?rfc symrefs='yes'?>
<?rfc sortrefs='yes' ?>
<?rfc compact='yes'?>
<?rfc subcompact='no' ?>
<?rfc text-list-symbols='-*o" ?>

<rfc ipr='pre5378Trust200902' docName="draft-ietf-lamps-rfc5750-bis-latest" category='std'>
  <front>
    <title abbrev="S/MIME 4.0 Certificate Handling">Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (S/ MIME) Version 4.0 Certificate Handling</title>
    <author fullname="Jim Schaad" initials="J." surname="Schaad">
      <organization>August Cellars</organization>
      <address>
        <email>ietf@augustcellars.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Blake Ramsdell" initials="B." surname="Ramsdell">
      <organization>Brute Squad Labs, Inc.</organization>
      <address>
        <email>blaker@gmail.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <author fullname="Sean Turner" initials="S." surname="Turner">
      <organization>sn3rd</organization>
      <address>
        <email>sean@sn3rd.com</email>
      </address>
    </author>
    <date/>
    <area>Security Area</area>
    <workgroup>LAMPS</workgroup>
    <keyword>S/MIME</keyword>
    <abstract>
      <t>
   This document specifies conventions for X.509 certificate usage by
   Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions (S/&wj;MIME) v4.0 agents.
   S/&wj;MIME provides a method to send and receive secure MIME messages,
   and certificates are an integral part of S/&wj;MIME agent processing.
   S/&wj;MIME agents validate certificates as described in RFC 5280, the
   Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure Certificate and CRL Profile.
   S/&wj;MIME agents must meet the certificate processing requirements in
   this document as well as those in RFC 5280.  This document obsoletes
   RFC 3850.
      </t>
    </abstract>
    <note title="Contributing to this document">
      <!-- RFC EDITOR - Please remove this note before publishing -->
      <t>
        The source for this draft is being maintained in GitHub.
        Suggested changes should be submitted as pull requests  at <eref target="https://github.com/lamps-wg/smime"/>.
        Instructions are on that page as well.
        Editorial changes can be managed in GitHub, but any substantial issues need to be discussed on the LAMPS mailing list.
      </t>
    </note>
  </front>
  <middle>

<section title="Introduction">
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME (Secure/Multipurpose Internet Mail Extensions) v4.0, described
   in <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-rfc5751-bis"/>, provides a method to send and receive secure MIME
   messages.  Before using a public key to provide security services,
   the S/&wj;MIME agent MUST verify that the public key is valid.  S/&wj;MIME
   agents MUST use PKIX certificates to validate public keys as
   described in the Internet X.509 Public Key Infrastructure (PKIX)
   Certificate and CRL Profile <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  S/&wj;MIME agents MUST meet the
   certificate processing requirements documented in this document in
   addition to those stated in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   This specification is compatible with the Cryptographic Message
   Syntax (CMS) RFC 5652 <xref target="RFC5652"/> in that it uses the data types defined by
   CMS.  It also inherits all the varieties of architectures for
   certificate-based key management supported by CMS.
  </t>
<section title="Definitions">
  <t>
   For the purposes of this document, the following definitions apply.
  </t>
  <t>
   ASN.1: Abstract Syntax Notation One, as defined in ITU-T X.680
   <xref target="X.680"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Attribute certificate (AC): An X.509 AC is a separate structure from
   a subject's public key X.509 certificate.  A subject may have
   multiple X.509 ACs associated with each of its public key X.509
   certificates.  Each X.509 AC binds one or more attributes with one of
   the subject's public key X.509 certificates.  The X.509 AC syntax is
   defined in <xref target="RFC5755"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Certificate: A type that binds an entity's name to a public key with
   a digital signature.  This type is defined in the Internet X.509
   Public Key Infrastructure (PKIX) Certificate and CRL Profile <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
   This type also contains the distinguished name of the certificate
   issuer (the signer), an issuer-specific serial number, the issuer's
   signature algorithm identifier, a validity period, and extensions
   also defined in that document.
  </t>
  <t>
   Certificate Revocation List (CRL): A type that contains information
   about certificates whose validity an issuer has prematurely revoked.
   The information consists of an issuer name, the time of issue, the
   next scheduled time of issue, a list of certificate serial numbers
   and their associated revocation times, and extensions as defined in
   <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  The CRL is signed by the issuer.  The type intended by this
   specification is the one defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agent: Software that interprets and processes S/&wj;MIME CMS
   objects, MIME body parts that contain CMS objects, or both.
  </t>
  <t>
   Sending agent: Software that creates S/&wj;MIME CMS objects, MIME body
   parts that contain CMS objects, or both.
  </t>
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME agent: User software that is a receiving agent, a sending
   agent, or both.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Conventions Used in This Document">
  <t>
   The key words "MUST", "MUST NOT", "REQUIRED", "SHALL", "SHALL NOT",
   "SHOULD", "SHOULD NOT", "RECOMMENDED", "MAY", and "OPTIONAL" in this
   document are to be interpreted as described in <xref target="RFC2119"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   We define the additional requirement levels:
   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="8">
     <t hangText="SHOULD+">    This term means the same as SHOULD.  However, the authors
              expect that a requirement marked as SHOULD+ will be
              promoted at some future time to be a MUST.
</t>
   <t hangText="SHOULD-">    This term means the same as SHOULD.  However, the authors
              expect that a requirement marked as SHOULD- will be
              demoted to a MAY in a future version of this document.
</t>
   <t hangText="MUST-">      This term means the same as MUST.  However, the authors
              expect that this requirement will no longer be a MUST in a
              future document.  Although its status will be determined
              at a later time, it is reasonable to expect that if a
              future revision of a document alters the status of a MUST-
              requirement, it will remain at least a SHOULD or a
              SHOULD-.
   </t>
   </list>
  </t>

  <t hangText="RSA">
     The term RSA in this document almost always refers to the PKCS#1 v1.5 RSA signature algorithm even when not qualified as such.
     There are a couple of places where it refers to the general RSA cryptographic operation, these can be determined from the context where it is used.
   </t>

</section>
<section title="Compatibility with Prior Practice S/MIME">
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME version 4.0 agents ought to attempt to have the greatest
   interoperability possible with agents for prior versions of S/&wj;MIME.
  </t>
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME version 2 is described in RFC 2311 through RFC 2315 inclusive
   <xref target="SMIMEv2"/>, S/&wj;MIME version 3 is described in RFC 2630 through RFC 2634
   inclusive and RFC 5035 <xref target="SMIMEv3"/>, and S/&wj;MIME version 3.1 is described
   in RFC 3850, RFC 3851, RFC 3852, RFC 2634, and RFC 5035 <xref target="SMIMEv3.1"/>.
   RFC 2311 also has historical information about the development of
   S/&wj;MIME.
  </t>
  <t>
    <xref target="historic"/> contains information about algorithms are were used for prior versions of S/MIME but are no longer considered to meet modern security standards.
    Support of these algorithms may be needed to support historic S/MIME messages but SHOULD NOT be used for new mail.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Changes from S/MIME v3 to S/MIME v3.1">
  <t>
   Version 1 and version 2 CRLs MUST be supported.
  </t>
  <t>
   Multiple certification authority (CA) certificates with the same
   subject and public key, but with overlapping validity periods, MUST
   be supported.
  </t>
  <t>
   Version 2 attribute certificates SHOULD be supported, and version 1
   attributes certificates MUST NOT be used.
  </t>
  <t>
   The use of the MD2 digest algorithm for certificate signatures is
   discouraged, and security language was added.
  </t>
  <t>
   Clarified use of email address use in certificates.  Certificates
   that do not contain an email address have no requirements for
   verifying the email address associated with the certificate.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agents SHOULD display certificate information when
   displaying the results of signature verification.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agents MUST NOT accept a signature made with a certificate
   that does not have the digitalSignature or nonRepudiation bit set.
  </t>
  <t>
   Clarifications for the interpretation of the key usage and extended
   key usage extensions.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Changes from S/MIME v3.1 to S/MIME v3.2">
<t>
   Conventions Used in This Document: Moved to Section 1.2. Added
   definitions for SHOULD+, SHOULD-, and MUST-.
   
   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">
     <t hangText="Section 1.1:">Updated ASN.1 definition and reference.</t>

     <t hangText="Section 1.3:">   Added text about v3.1 RFCs.</t>

     <t hangText="Section 3:">     Aligned email address text with RFC 5280.  Updated
                  note to indicate emailAddress IA5String upper bound is
                  255 characters.  Added text about matching email
                  addresses.
</t>
   <t hangText="Section 4.2:">   Added text to indicate how S/&wj;MIME agents locate the
                  correct user certificate.
</t>



   <t hangText="Section 4.3:">   RSA with SHA-256 (PKCS #1 v1.5) added as MUST; DSA
                  with SHA-256 added as SHOULD+; RSA with SHA-1, DSA
                  with SHA-1, and RSA with MD5 changed to SHOULD-; and
                  RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256 added as SHOULD+.  Updated key
                  sizes and changed pointer to PKIX RFCs.
</t>
   <t hangText="Section 4.4.1:"> Aligned with PKIX on use of basic constraints
                  extension in CA certificates.  Clarified which
                  extension is used to constrain end entities from using
                  their keys to perform issuing authority operations.
</t>
   <t hangText="Section 5:">     Updated security considerations.</t>

   <t hangText="Section 7:">     Moved references from Appendix B to Section 6.
                  Updated the references.
</t>
   <t hangText="Appendix A:">    Moved Appendix A to Appendix B.  Added Appendix A to
                  move S/&wj;MIME v2 Certificate Handling to Historic
                  Status.
   </t>
   </list>
</t>
</section>
<section title="Changes since S/MIME 3.2">
  <t>
   <list style="hanging" hangIndent="12">
      <t hangText="Section 3:">
        Require support for internationalized email addresses.
      </t>
      <t hangText="Section 4.3:">
        Mandated support for ECDSA with P-256 and Ed25519.
        Moved algorithms with SHA-1 and MD5 to historical status.
        Moved DSA support to historical status.
        Increased lower bounds on RSA key sizes.
      </t>
      <t hangText="Appendix A:">
        Add a new appendix for algorithms that are now considered to be historical.
      </t>
    </list>
  </t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="CMS Options">
<t>
   The CMS message format allows for a wide variety of options in
   content and algorithm support.  This section puts forth a number of
   support requirements and recommendations in order to achieve a base
   level of interoperability among all S/&wj;MIME implementations.  Most of
   the CMS format for S/&wj;MIME messages is defined in <xref target="RFC5751"/>.
</t>
<section title="Certificate Revocation Lists">
<t>
   Receiving agents MUST support the Certificate Revocation List (CRL)
   format defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  If sending agents include CRLs in outgoing
   messages, the CRL format defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/> MUST be used.  In all
   cases, both v1 and v2 CRLs MUST be supported.
  </t>
  <t>
   All agents MUST be capable of performing revocation checks using CRLs
   as specified in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  All agents MUST perform revocation status
   checking in accordance with <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  Receiving agents MUST recognize
   CRLs in received S/&wj;MIME messages.
  </t>
  <t>
   Agents SHOULD store CRLs received in messages for use in processing
   later messages.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Certificate Choices">
<t>
   Receiving agents MUST support v1 X.509 and v3 X.509 certificates as
   profiled in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  End-entity certificates MAY include an Internet
   mail address, as described in Section 3.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agents SHOULD support X.509 version 2 attribute
   certificates.  See <xref target="RFC5755"/> for details about the profile for
   attribute certificates.
  </t>
<section title="Historical Note about CMS Certificates">
<t>
   The CMS message format supports a choice of certificate formats for
   public key content types: PKIX, PKCS #6 extended certificates
   <xref target="PKCS6"/>, and PKIX attribute certificates.
  </t>
  <t>
   The PKCS #6 format is not in widespread use.  In addition, PKIX
   certificate extensions address much of the same functionality and
   flexibility as was intended in the PKCS #6.  Thus, sending and
   receiving agents MUST NOT use PKCS #6 extended certificates.
  </t>
  <t>
   X.509 version 1 attribute certificates are also not widely
   implemented, and have been superseded with version 2 attribute
   certificates.  Sending agents MUST NOT send version 1 attribute
   certificates.
  </t>
</section>
</section>
<section title="CertificateSet">
<t>
   Receiving agents MUST be able to handle an arbitrary number of
   certificates of arbitrary relationship to the message sender and to
   each other in arbitrary order.  In many cases, the certificates
   included in a signed message may represent a chain of certification
   from the sender to a particular root.  There may be, however,
   situations where the certificates in a signed message may be
   unrelated and included for convenience.
  </t>
  <t>
   Sending agents SHOULD include any certificates for the user's public
   key(s) and associated issuer certificates.  This increases the
   likelihood that the intended recipient can establish trust in the
   originator's public key(s).  This is especially important when
   sending a message to recipients that may not have access to the
   sender's public key through any other means or when sending a signed
   message to a new recipient.  The inclusion of certificates in
   outgoing messages can be omitted if S/&wj;MIME objects are sent within a
   group of correspondents that has established access to each other's
   certificates by some other means such as a shared directory or manual
   certificate distribution.  Receiving S/&wj;MIME agents SHOULD be able to
   handle messages without certificates using a database or directory
   lookup scheme.
  </t>
  <t>

   A sending agent SHOULD include at least one chain of certificates up
   to, but not including, a certification authority (CA) that it
   believes that the recipient may trust as authoritative.  A receiving
   agent MUST be able to handle an arbitrarily large number of
   certificates and chains.
  </t>
  <t>
   Agents MAY send CA certificates, that is, cross-certificates, self-
   issued certificates, and self-signed certificates.  Note that
   receiving agents SHOULD NOT simply trust any self-signed certificates
   as valid CAs, but SHOULD use some other mechanism to determine if
   this is a CA that should be trusted.  Also note that when
   certificates contain Digital Signature Algorithm (DSA) public keys
   the parameters may be located in the root certificate.  This would
   require that the recipient possess both the end-entity certificate
   and the root certificate to perform a signature verification, and is
   a valid example of a case where transmitting the root certificate may
   be required.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agents MUST support chaining based on the distinguished
   name fields.  Other methods of building certificate chains MAY be
   supported.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving agents SHOULD support the decoding of X.509 attribute
   certificates included in CMS objects.  All other issues regarding the
   generation and use of X.509 attribute certificates are outside of the
   scope of this specification.  One specification that addresses
   attribute certificate use is defined in <xref target="RFC3114"/>.
  </t>
</section>
 </section>
 <section title="Using Distinguished Names for Internet Mail">
   <t>
     
     End-entity certificates MAY contain an Internet mail address.
     Email addresses retricted to 7-bit ASCII characters are encoded as described in Section 4.2.1.6 of <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
     Internationalized Email address names are encoded as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-eai-addresses"/>.
     The email address SHOULD be in the subjectAltName extension, and SHOULD NOT be in the subject distinguished name.
   </t>
   
  <t>
    Receiving agents MUST recognize and accept certificates that contain no email address.
    Agents are allowed to provide an alternative mechanism for associating an email address with a certificate that does not contain an email address, such as through the use of the agent's address book, if available.
    Receiving agents MUST recognize both ASCII and internationalized email addresses in the subjectAltName field.
    Receiving agents MUST recognize email addresses in the Distinguished Name field in the PKCS #9 <xref target="RFC2985"/> emailAddress attribute:
  </t>

  <figure>
      <artwork>
pkcs-9-at-emailAddress OBJECT IDENTIFIER ::=
 { iso(1) member-body(2) us(840) rsadsi(113549) pkcs(1) pkcs-9(9) 1 }
      </artwork>
  </figure>

  <t>
    Note that this attribute MUST be encoded as IA5String and has an  upper bound of 255 characters.
    The right side of the email address SHOULD be treated as ASCII-case-insensitive.
  </t>

  <t>
    Comparing of email addresses is fraught with peril.
    <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-eai-addresses"/> defines the procedure for doing comparison of Internationalized email addresses.
    For ASCII email addresses the domain component (right-hand side of the '@') MUST be compared using a case-insensitive function.
    The local name component (left-hand side of the '@') SHOULD be compared using a case-insensitive function.
    Some localities may perform other transformations on the local name component before doing the comparison, however an S/MIME client cannot know what specific localities do.
  </t>
  
  <t>
    Sending agents SHOULD make the address in the From or Sender header in a mail message match an Internet mail address in the signer's certificate.
    Receiving agents MUST check that the address in the From or Sender header of a mail message matches an Internet mail address in the signer's certificate, if mail addresses are present in the certificate.
    A receiving agent SHOULD provide some explicit alternate processing of the message if this comparison fails, which may be to display a message that shows the recipient the addresses in the certificate or other certificate details.
  </t>
  <t>
   A receiving agent SHOULD display a subject name or other certificate details when displaying an indication of successful or unsuccessful signature verification.
  </t>
  <t>
   All subject and issuer names MUST be populated (i.e., not an empty SEQUENCE) in S/&wj;MIME-compliant X.509 certificates, except that the subject distinguished name (DN) in a user's (i.e., end-entity) certificate MAY be an empty SEQUENCE in which case the subjectAltName extension will include the subject's identifier and MUST be marked as critical.
  </t>
 </section>
<section title="Certificate Processing">
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME agents need to provide some certificate retrieval mechanism in
   order to gain access to certificates for recipients of digital
   envelopes.  There are many ways to implement certificate retrieval
   mechanisms.  <xref target="X.500"/> directory service is an excellent example of a
   certificate retrieval-only mechanism that is compatible with classic
   X.500 Distinguished Names.  Another method under consideration by the
   IETF is to provide certificate retrieval services as part of the
   existing Domain Name System (DNS).  Until such mechanisms are widely
   used, their utility may be limited by the small number of the
   correspondent's certificates that can be retrieved.  At a minimum,
   for initial S/&wj;MIME deployment, a user agent could automatically
   generate a message to an intended recipient requesting the
   recipient's certificate in a signed return message.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving and sending agents SHOULD also provide a mechanism to allow
   a user to "store and protect" certificates for correspondents in such
   a way so as to guarantee their later retrieval.  In many
   environments, it may be desirable to link the certificate
   retrieval/storage mechanisms together in some sort of certificate
   database.  In its simplest form, a certificate database would be
   local to a particular user and would function in a similar way as an
   "address book" that stores a user's frequent correspondents.  In this
   way, the certificate retrieval mechanism would be limited to the
   certificates that a user has stored (presumably from incoming
   messages).  A comprehensive certificate retrieval/storage solution
   may combine two or more mechanisms to allow the greatest flexibility
   and utility to the user.  For instance, a secure Internet mail agent
   may resort to checking a centralized certificate retrieval mechanism
   for a certificate if it cannot be found in a user's local certificate
   storage/retrieval database.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving and sending agents SHOULD provide a mechanism for the
   import and export of certificates, using a CMS certs-only message.
   This allows for import and export of full certificate chains as
   opposed to just a single certificate.  This is described in
   <xref target="RFC5751"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Agents MUST handle multiple valid certification authority (CA)
   certificates containing the same subject name and the same public
   keys but with overlapping validity intervals.
  </t>
<section title="Certificate Revocation Lists">
  <t>
   In general, it is always better to get the latest CRL information
   from a CA than to get information stored away from incoming messages.
   A receiving agent SHOULD have access to some CRL retrieval mechanism
   in order to gain access to certificate revocation information when
   validating certification paths.  A receiving or sending agent SHOULD
   also provide a mechanism to allow a user to store incoming
   certificate revocation information for correspondents in such a way
   so as to guarantee its later retrieval.
  </t>
  <t>
   Receiving and sending agents SHOULD retrieve and utilize CRL
   information every time a certificate is verified as part of a
   certification path validation even if the certificate was already
   verified in the past.  However, in many instances (such as off-line
   verification) access to the latest CRL information may be difficult
   or impossible.  The use of CRL information, therefore, may be
   dictated by the value of the information that is protected.  The
   value of the CRL information in a particular context is beyond the
   scope of this specification but may be governed by the policies
   associated with particular certification paths.
  </t>
  <t>
   All agents MUST be capable of performing revocation checks using CRLs
   as specified in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  All agents MUST perform revocation status
   checking in accordance with <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  Receiving agents MUST recognize
   CRLs in received S/&wj;MIME messages.
  </t>

</section>

<section title="Certificate Path Validation">
  <t>
   In creating a user agent for secure messaging, certificate, CRL, and
   certification path validation SHOULD be highly automated while still
   acting in the best interests of the user.  Certificate, CRL, and path
   validation MUST be performed as per <xref target="RFC5280"/> when validating a
   correspondent's public key.  This is necessary before using a public
   key to provide security services such as verifying a signature,
   encrypting a content-encryption key (e.g., RSA), or forming a
   pairwise symmetric key (e.g., Diffie-Hellman) to be used to encrypt
   or decrypt a content-encryption key.
  </t>
  <t>
   Certificates and CRLs are made available to the path validation
   procedure in two ways: a) incoming messages, and b) certificate and
   CRL retrieval mechanisms.  Certificates and CRLs in incoming messages
   are not required to be in any particular order nor are they required
   to be in any way related to the sender or recipient of the message
   (although in most cases they will be related to the sender).
   Incoming certificates and CRLs SHOULD be cached for use in path
   validation and optionally stored for later use.  This temporary
   certificate and CRL cache SHOULD be used to augment any other
   certificate and CRL retrieval mechanisms for path validation on
   incoming signed messages.
  </t>
  <t>
   When verifying a signature and the certificates that are included in
   the message, if a signingCertificate attribute from RFC 2634 <xref target="ESS"/> or
   a signingCertificateV2 attribute from RFC 5035 <xref target="ESS"/> is found in an
   S/&wj;MIME message, it SHALL be used to identify the signer's
   certificate.  Otherwise, the certificate is identified in an S/&wj;MIME
   message, either using the issuerAndSerialNumber, which identifies the
   signer's certificate by the issuer's distinguished name and the
   certificate serial number, or the subjectKeyIdentifier, which
   identifies the signer's certificate by a key identifier.
  </t>
  <t>
   When decrypting an encrypted message, if a
   SMIMEEncryptionKeyPreference attribute is found in an encapsulating
   SignedData, it SHALL be used to identify the originator's certificate
   found in OriginatorInfo.  See <xref target="RFC5652"/> for the CMS fields that reference
   the originator's and recipient's certificates.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Certificate and CRL Signing Algorithms and Key Sizes">
  <t>
   Certificates and Certificate Revocation Lists (CRLs) are signed by
   the certificate issuer.  Receiving agents:
   <list style="symbols">

     <t>MUST support ECDSA with curve P-256 with SHA-256.</t>

     <t>MUST support EdDSA with curve 25519 using PureEdDSA mode.</t>

     <t>MUST- support RSA with SHA-256.</t>

     <t>SHOULD support RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256.</t>

     <t>MUST NOT support EdDSA using Pre-hash mode.</t>

   </list>
   
  </t>

  <t>
    Implementations SHOULD use deterministic generation for the parameter 'k' for ECDSA as outlined in <xref target="RFC6979"/>.
    EdDSA is defined to generate this parameter deterministically.
  </t>
  
  <t>
   The following are the RSA and RSASSA-PSS key size requirements for
   S/&wj;MIME receiving agents during certificate and CRL signature
   verification:
  </t>
  
  <figure>
    <artwork>
        key size &lt;= 2047 : SHOULD NOT (see Historic Considerations)
2048 &lt;= key size &lt;= 4096 : MUST (see Security Considerations)
4096 &lt;  key size         : MAY  (see Security Considerations)
    </artwork>
  </figure>

  <!--  Russ wants to replace this paragraph 
  <t>
   For 1024-bit through 3072-bit RSA with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC4055"/> and <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> with Change Notice 1,
   and for 4096-bit RSA with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC4055"/> and <xref target="RFC3447"/>.
   In either case, the first reference provides the signature algorithm's object identifier and the second provides the signature algorithm's definition.
  </t>
   -->
  <!-- With the following two paragraphs -->
       <t>
         The signature algorithm object identifiers for RSA PKCS#1 v1.5 and RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256 using 1024-bit through 3072-bit public keys are specified in [RFC4055] and the signature algorithm definition is found in [FIPS186-2] with Change Notice 1.
       </t>

      <t>
        The signature algorithm object identifiers for RSA PKCS#1 v1.5 and RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256 using 4096-bit public keys are specified in [RFC4055] and the signature algorithm definition is found in [RFC3447].
      </t>
       


  <t>
    For RSASSA-PSS with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC4056"/>.
  </t>

  <t>
    For ECDSA see <xref target="RFC5758"/> and <xref target="RFC6090"/>.
    The first reference provides the signature algorithm's object identifier and the second provides the signature algorithm's definition.
    Curves other than curve P-256 MAY be used as well.
  </t>

  <t>
    For EdDSA see <xref target="I-D.ietf-curdle-pkix"/> and <xref target="I-D.irtf-cfrg-eddsa"/>.
    The first reference provides the signature algorithm's object identifier and the second provides the signature algorithm's definition.
    Other curves than curve 25519 MAY be used as well.
  </t>
  
</section>
<section title="PKIX Certificate Extensions">
  <t>
   PKIX describes an extensible framework in which the basic certificate
   information can be extended and describes how such extensions can be
   used to control the process of issuing and validating certificates.
   The PKIX Working Group has ongoing efforts to identify and create
   extensions that have value in particular certification environments.
   Further, there are active efforts underway to issue PKIX certificates
   for business purposes.  This document identifies the minimum required
   set of certificate extensions that have the greatest value in the
   S/&wj;MIME environment.  The syntax and semantics of all the identified
   extensions are defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.
  </t>
  <t>
   Sending and receiving agents MUST correctly handle the basic
   constraints, key usage, authority key identifier, subject key
   identifier, and subject alternative names certificate extensions when
   they appear in end-entity and CA certificates.  Some mechanism SHOULD
   exist to gracefully handle other certificate extensions when they
   appear in end-entity or CA certificates.
  </t>
  <t>
   Certificates issued for the S/&wj;MIME environment SHOULD NOT contain any
   critical extensions (extensions that have the critical field set to
   TRUE) other than those listed here.  These extensions SHOULD be
   marked as non-critical unless the proper handling of the extension is
   deemed critical to the correct interpretation of the associated
   certificate.  Other extensions may be included, but those extensions
   SHOULD NOT be marked as critical.
  </t>
  <t>
   Interpretation and syntax for all extensions MUST follow <xref target="RFC5280"/>,
   unless otherwise specified here.
  </t>
<section title="Basic Constraints">
  <t>
   The basic constraints extension serves to delimit the role and
   position that an issuing authority or end-entity certificate plays in
   a certification path.
  </t>
  <t>
   For example, certificates issued to CAs and subordinate CAs contain a
   basic constraint extension that identifies them as issuing authority
   certificates.  End-entity certificates contain the key usage
   extension that restrains end entities from using the key when
   performing issuing authority operations (see Section 4.4.2).
  </t>
  <t>
   As per <xref target="RFC5280"/>, certificates MUST contain a basicConstraints extension
   in CA certificates, and SHOULD NOT contain that extension in end-
   entity certificates.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Key Usage Certificate Extension">
  <t>
   The key usage extension serves to limit the technical purposes for
   which a public key listed in a valid certificate may be used.
   Issuing authority certificates may contain a key usage extension that
   restricts the key to signing certificates, certificate revocation
   lists, and other data.
  </t>
  <t>
   For example, a certification authority may create subordinate issuer
   certificates that contain a key usage extension that specifies that
   the corresponding public key can be used to sign end user
   certificates and sign CRLs.
  </t>
  <t>
   If a key usage extension is included in a PKIX certificate, then it
   MUST be marked as critical.
  </t>
  <t>
   S/&wj;MIME receiving agents MUST NOT accept the signature of a message if
   it was verified using a certificate that contains the key usage
   extension without either the digitalSignature or nonRepudiation bit
   set.  Sometimes S/&wj;MIME is used as a secure message transport for
   applications beyond interpersonal messaging.  In such cases, the
   S/&wj;MIME-enabled application can specify additional requirements
   concerning the digitalSignature or nonRepudiation bits within this
   extension.
  </t>
  <t>
   If the key usage extension is not specified, receiving clients MUST
   presume that the digitalSignature and nonRepudiation bits are set.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Subject Alternative Name">
  <t>
   The subject alternative name extension is used in S/&wj;MIME as the
   preferred means to convey the email address(es) that correspond(s) to
   the entity for this certificate.
   Any ASCII email addresses present MUST be encoded using the rfc822Name CHOICE of the GeneralName type as described in <xref target="RFC5280"/>, Section 4.2.1.6.
   Any internationalized email addresses present MUST be encoded using the otherName CHOICE of the GeneralName type as described in <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-eai-addresses"/>, Section 3.
   Since the SubjectAltName type is a SEQUENCE OF GeneralName, multiple email addresses MAY be present.
  </t>
</section>
<section title="Extended Key Usage Extension">
  <t>
   The extended key usage extension also serves to limit the technical
   purposes for which a public key listed in a valid certificate may be
   used.  The set of technical purposes for the certificate therefore
   are the intersection of the uses indicated in the key usage and
   extended key usage extensions.
  </t>
  <t>
   For example, if the certificate contains a key usage extension
   indicating digital signature and an extended key usage extension that
   includes the email protection OID, then the certificate may be used
   for signing but not encrypting S/&wj;MIME messages.  If the certificate
   contains a key usage extension indicating digital signature but no
   extended key usage extension, then the certificate may also be used
   to sign but not encrypt S/&wj;MIME messages.
  </t>
  <t>





   If the extended key usage extension is present in the certificate,
   then interpersonal message S/&wj;MIME receiving agents MUST check that it
   contains either the emailProtection or the anyExtendedKeyUsage OID as
   defined in <xref target="RFC5280"/>.  S/&wj;MIME uses other than interpersonal messaging
   MAY require the explicit presence of the extended key usage extension
   or other OIDs to be present in the extension or both.
  </t>
</section>
</section>
 </section>
 <section title="Security Considerations">
   <t>
   All of the security issues faced by any cryptographic application
   must be faced by a S/&wj;MIME agent.  Among these issues are protecting
   the user's private key, preventing various attacks, and helping the
   user avoid mistakes such as inadvertently encrypting a message for
   the wrong recipient.  The entire list of security considerations is
   beyond the scope of this document, but some significant concerns are
   listed here.
  </t>
  <t>
   When processing certificates, there are many situations where the
   processing might fail.  Because the processing may be done by a user
   agent, a security gateway, or other program, there is no single way
   to handle such failures.  Just because the methods to handle the
   failures have not been listed, however, the reader should not assume
   that they are not important.  The opposite is true: if a certificate
   is not provably valid and associated with the message, the processing
   software should take immediate and noticeable steps to inform the end
   user about it.
  </t>
  <t>
   Some of the many places where signature and certificate checking
   might fail include:
   <list style="symbols">
     <t>no Internet mail addresses in a certificate match the sender of a
     message, if the certificate contains at least one mail address</t>

     <t>no certificate chain leads to a trusted CA</t>

     <t>no ability to check the CRL for a certificate</t>

     <t>an invalid CRL was received</t>

     <t>the CRL being checked is expired</t>

     <t>the certificate is expired</t>

     <t>the certificate has been revoked</t>
   </list>



  </t>
  <t>
   There are certainly other instances where a certificate may be
   invalid, and it is the responsibility of the processing software to
   check them all thoroughly, and to decide what to do if the check
   fails.
  </t>
  <t>
   It is possible for there to be multiple unexpired CRLs for a CA.  If
   an agent is consulting CRLs for certificate validation, it SHOULD
   make sure that the most recently issued CRL for that CA is consulted,
   since an S/&wj;MIME message sender could deliberately include an older
   unexpired CRL in an S/&wj;MIME message.  This older CRL might not include
   recently revoked certificates, which might lead an agent to accept a
   certificate that has been revoked in a subsequent CRL.
  </t>
  <t>
   When determining the time for a certificate validity check, agents
   have to be careful to use a reliable time.  Unless it is from a
   trusted agent, this time MUST NOT be the SigningTime attribute found
   in an S/&wj;MIME message.  For most sending agents, the SigningTime
   attribute could be deliberately set to direct the receiving agent to
   check a CRL that could have out-of-date revocation status for a
   certificate, or cause an improper result when checking the Validity
   field of a certificate.
  </t>
  <t>
   In addition to the Security Considerations identified in <xref target="RFC5280"/>,
   caution should be taken when processing certificates that have not
   first been validated to a trust anchor.  Certificates could be
   manufactured by untrusted sources for the purpose of mounting denial
   of service or other attacks.  For example, keys selected to require
   excessive cryptographic processing, or extensive lists of CRL
   Distribution Point (CDP) and/or Authority Information Access (AIA)
   addresses in the certificate, could be used to mount denial-of-
   service attacks.  Similarly, attacker-specified CDP and/or AIA
   addresses could be included in fake certificates to allow the
   originator to detect receipt of the message even if signature
   verification fails.
  </t>
  <!--
      The start of this paragraph is no longer true.

  <t>
   The 4096-bit RSA key size requirement for certificate and CRL
   verification is larger than the 2048-bit RSA key sizes for message
   signature generation/verification or message encryption/decryption in
   <xref target="RFC5751"/> because many root CAs included in certificate stores have
   already issued root certificates with the 4096-bit key.
   The standard
   that defines comparable key sizes for DSA is not yet available.
   In
   particular, <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> without Change Notice 1 allowed DSA key sizes
   between 512 and 1024 bits, <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> with Change Notice 1 only
   allowed DSA key sizes of 1024 bits, and <xref target="FIPS186-3"/> allowed DSA key
   sizes from 1024 to 3072 bits.
   Further, 4096-bit keys are normally
   only used by Root certificates and not by subordinate CA
   certificates, thereby lengthening the root CA certificate's validity
   period.
   </t>
   -->
  <t>
   RSA keys of less than 2048  bits are now considered by many
   experts to be cryptographically insecure (due to advances in
   computing power), and should no longer be used to sign certificates
   or CRLs.  Such keys were previously considered secure, so processing
   previously received signed and encrypted mail may require processing
   certificates or CRLs signed with weak keys.  Implementations that
   wish to support previous versions of S/&wj;MIME or process old messages
   need to consider the security risks that result from accepting
   certificates and CRLs with smaller key sizes (e.g., spoofed
   certificates) versus the costs of denial of service.  If an
   implementation supports verification of certificates or CRLs
   generated with RSA and DSA keys of less than 2048 bits, it MUST warn
   the user.  Implementers should consider providing a stronger warning
   for weak signatures on certificates and CRLs associated with newly
   received messages than the one provided for certificates and CRLs
   associated with previously stored messages.  Server implementations
   (e.g., secure mail list servers) where user warnings are not
   appropriate SHOULD reject messages with weak cryptography.
  </t>

  <t>
   If an implementation is concerned about compliance with National
   Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST) key size
   recommendations, then see <xref target="SP800-57"/>.
  </t>
 </section>
 </middle>
 <back>
   <!--

        <displayreference target="RFC3114" use="SECLABEL"/>
        <displayreference target="RFC5652" use="CMS"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC5280" use="KEYM"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC3279" use="KEYMALG"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC5758" use="KEYMALG2"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC2119" use="MUSTSHOULD"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC3447" use="PKCS1"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC2985" use="PKCS9"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC4056" use="RSAPSS"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC4055" use="RSAOAEP"/>
       <displayreference target="RFC5751" use="SMIME-MSG"/>
   -->
        
   <references title="Normative References">
     &rfc2119;
     &rfc2634;
     &rfc2985;
     &rfc3447;
     &rfc4056;
     &rfc4055;
     &rfc5035;
     &rfc5280;
     &rfc5751;
     &rfc5755;
     &rfc5758;
     &rfc3279;
     &rfc5652;
     
        <reference anchor="FIPS186-2">
          <front>
            <title>Digital Signature Standard (DSS) [With Change Notice 1]</title>
            <author><organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</organization></author>
            <date month="January" year="2000"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Federal Information Processing Standards Publication"
                      value="186-2"/>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="FIPS186-3">
          <front>
            <title>Digital Signature Standard (DSS)</title>
            <author><organization>National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)</organization></author>
            <date month="June" year="2009"/>
          </front>
          <seriesInfo name="Federal Information Processing Standards Publication"
                      value="186-3"/>
        </reference>
     
        <reference anchor="X.680">
          <front>
            <title>Information Technology - Abstract Syntax
            Notation One (ASN.1):  Specification of basic notation.
            ITU-T Recommendation X.680 (2002) | ISO/IEC 8824-1:2002. 
            </title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>
   
        <reference anchor="SMIMEv3.2">
          <front>
            <title>S/MIME version 3.2</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This group of documents represents S/MIME version 3.2.
            This set of documents are <xref target="RFC2634"/>, <xref target="RFC5750"/>, [[This Document]], <xref target="RFC5652"/>,  and <xref target="RFC5035"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="SMIMEv4.0">
          <front>
            <title>S/MIME version 4.0</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This group of documents represents S/MIME version 4.0.
            This set of documents are <xref target="RFC2634"/>, <xref target="I-D.ietf-lamps-rfc5751-bis"/>, [[This Document]], <xref target="RFC5652"/>,  and <xref target="RFC5035"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>
        
        &rfc5750;

        &rfc5751bis;
        &eaiAddress;
        &rfc6979;
        
   </references>

   <references title="Informational References">
     &rfc2311;  &rfc2312; &rfc2313; &rfc2314; &rfc2315;
     &rfc2630;  &rfc2631; &rfc2632; &rfc2633;
     &rfc3850;  &rfc3851; &rfc3852;
     &rfc3114;

        <!--
            <referencegroup target="MIME-SPEC">
            &rfc2045;
            &rfc2046;
            &rfc2047;
            &rfc2049;
            &rfc4288;
            &rfc4289;
            </referencegroup>
        <reference anchor="MIME-SPEC">
          <front>
            <title>MIME Message Specifications</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This is the set of documents that define how to use MIME.
            This set of documents is <xref target="RFC2045"/>, <xref target="RFC2046"/>, <xref target="RFC2047"/>, <xref target="RFC2049"/>, <xref target="RFC4288"/>, and <xref target="RFC4289"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>
        -->

        <!--
        <referencegroup target="ESS">
          &rfc2634;
          &rfc5035;
          </referencegroup>
          -->
        <reference anchor="ESS">
          <front>
            <title>Enhanced Security Services for S/ MIME</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This is the set of documents dealing with enhanged security services and refers to <xref target="RFC2634"/> and <xref target="RFC5035"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>

        <reference anchor="PKCS6">
       <front>
         <title>PKCS #6: Extended-Certificate Syntax Standard</title>
         <author><organization>RSA Laboratories</organization></author>
         <date month="November" year="1993"/>
       </front>
     </reference>
         
        <reference anchor="SP800-57">
          <front>
            <title>
              Special Publication 800-57: Recommendation for Key
              Management
            </title>
            <author><organization>
              National Institute of Standards and Technology (NIST)
            </organization>
            </author>
            <date               month="August" year="2005"/>
          </front>
        </reference>
        
        <reference anchor="X.500">
          <front>
            <title>ITU-T Recommendation X.500 (1997) | ISO/IEC 9594-
                1:1997, Information technology - Open Systems
                Interconnection - The Directory:  Overview of concepts,
            models and services.</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
        </reference>

        <!--
        <referencegroup target="SMIMEv2">
          &rfc2311;
          &rfc2312;
          &rfc2313;
          &rfc2314;
          &rfc2315;
        </referencegroup>
        -->
        <reference anchor="SMIMEv2">
          <front>
            <title>S/MIME version v2</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This group of documents represents S/MIME version 2.
            This set of documents are <xref target="RFC2311"/>, <xref target="RFC2312"/>, <xref target="RFC2313"/>, <xref target="RFC2314"/>, and <xref target="RFC2315"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>

      <!--
        <referencegroup target="SMIMEv3">
          &rfc2630;
          &rfc2631;
          &rfc2632;
          &rfc2633;
          &rfc2634;
          &rfc5035;
          </referencegroup>
          -->

        <reference anchor="SMIMEv3">
          <front>
            <title>S/MIME version 3</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This group of documents represents S/MIME version 3.
            This set of documents are <xref target="RFC2630"/>, <xref target="RFC2631"/>, <xref target="RFC2632"/>, <xref target="RFC2633"/>, <xref target="RFC2634"/>, and <xref target="RFC5035"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>

        <!--
        <referencegroup target="SMIMEv3.1">
          &rfc2634;
          &rfc3850;
          &rfc3851;
          &rfc3852;
          &rfc5035;
          </referencegroup>
          -->

        <reference anchor="SMIMEv3.1">
          <front>
            <title>S/MIME version 3.1</title>
            <author/>
            <date/>
          </front>
          <annotation>
            This group of documents represents S/MIME version 3.1.
            This set of documents are <xref target="RFC2634"/>, <xref target="RFC3850"/>, <xref target="RFC3851"/>, <xref target="RFC3852"/>,  and <xref target="RFC5035"/>.
          </annotation>
        </reference>

        &rfc6194;
        &rfc6151;
        &rfc6090;
        &eddsa;
        &curdlePkix;
        
</references>

<section title="Historic Considerations" anchor="historic">
  <section title="Signature Algorithms and Key Sizes">
    <t>
      There are a number of problems with validating certificates on sufficiently historic messages.
      For this reason it is strongly suggested that UAs treat these certificates differently from those on current messages.
      These problems include:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          CAs are not required to keep certificates on a CRL beyond one update after a certificate has expired.
          This means that unless CRLs are cached as part of the message it is not always possible to check if a certificate has been revoked.
          The same problems exist with OCSP responses as they may be based on a CRL rather than on the certificate database.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          RSA and DSA keys of less than 2048 bits are now considered by many experts to be cryptographically insecure (due to advances in computing power).
          Such keys were previously considered secure, so processing of historic  certificates  will often result in the use of weak keys.
          Implementations that wish to support previous versions of S/&wj;MIME or process old messages need to consider the security risks that result from smaller key sizes (e.g., spoofed messages) versus the costs of denial of service.
          <vspace blankLines="1"/>
          <xref target="SMIMEv3.1"/> set the lower limit on suggested key sizes for creating and validation at 1024 bits.
          Prior to that the lower bound on key sizes was 512 bits.
        </t>
        
        <t>
          Hash functions used to validate signatures on historic messages may longer be considered to be secure (see below).
          While there are not currently any known practical pre-image or second pre-image attacks against MD5 or SHA&nbhy;1, the fact they are no longer considered to be collision resistent the security levels of the signatures are generally considered suspect.
        </t>
        
      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
      The following algorithms have been called out for some level of support by previous S/MIME specifications:
      <list style="symbols">
        <t>
          RSA with MD5 was dropped in <xref target="SMIMEv4.0"/>.
          MD5 is no longer considered to be secure as it is no longer collision-resistant.
          Details can be found in <xref target="RFC6151"/>.
        </t>
        <t>
          RSA and DSA with SHA-1 were dropped in <xref target="SMIMEv4.0"/>.
          SHA-1 is nolonger considered to be secure as it is no longer collision-resistant.
          The IETF statement on SHA-1 can be found in <xref target="RFC6194"/> but it is out-of-date relative to the most recent advances.
        </t>
        <t>
          DSA with SHA-256 support was dropped in <xref target="SMIMEv4.0"/>.
          DSA was dropped as part of a general movement from discrete logarithms to elliptic curves.
          Issues have come up dealing with small group attacks and with non-deterministic generation of the parameter 'k' (see <xref target="RFC6979"/>).
        </t>

      </list>
    </t>

    <t>
   For 512-bit RSA with SHA-1 see <xref target="RFC3279"/> and <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> without
   Change Notice 1, for 512-bit RSA with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC4055"/> and
   <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> without Change Notice 1.
    </t>

    <t>
      For 512-bit DSA with SHA-1 see <xref target="RFC3279"/> and <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> without
      Change Notice 1, for 512-bit DSA with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC5758"/> and
      <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> without Change Notice 1, for 1024-bit DSA with SHA-1 see
      <xref target="RFC3279"/> and <xref target="FIPS186-2"/> with Change Notice 1, for 1024-bit through
      3072 DSA with SHA-256 see <xref target="RFC5758"/> and <xref target="FIPS186-3"/>.  In either
      case, the first reference provides the signature algorithm's object
      identifier and the second provides the signature algorithm's
      definition.
    </t>
  </section>
</section>

<section title="Moving S/MIME v2 Certificate Handling to Historic Status">
  <t>
   The S/&wj;MIME v3 <xref target="SMIMEv3"/>, v3.1 <xref target="SMIMEv3.1"/>, v3.2 <xref target="SMIMEv3.2"/>, and v4.0 (this document)
   are backwards compatible with the S/&wj;MIME v2 Certificate Handling
   Specification <xref target="SMIMEv2"/>, with the exception of the algorithms
   (dropped RC2/40 requirement and added DSA and RSASSA-PSS
   requirements).  Therefore, it is recommended that RFC 2312 <xref target="SMIMEv2"/>
   be moved to Historic status.
  </t>
</section>

<section title="Acknowledgments">
  <t>
   Many thanks go out to the other authors of the S/&wj;MIME v2 RFC: Steve
   Dusse, Paul Hoffman, and Jeff Weinstein.  Without v2, there wouldn't
   be a v3, v3.1, v3.2 or v4.0.
  </t>
  <t>
   A number of the members of the S/&wj;MIME Working Group have also worked
   very hard and contributed to this document.  Any list of people is
   doomed to omission, and for that I apologize.  In alphabetical order,
   the following people stand out in my mind because they made direct
   contributions to this document.
  </t>
  <t>
   Bill Flanigan, Trevor Freeman, Elliott Ginsburg, Alfred Hoenes, Paul
   Hoffman, Russ Housley, David P. Kemp, Michael Myers, John Pawling, and
   Denis Pinkas.
  </t>

  <t>
    The version 4 update to the S/&wj;MIME documents was done under the auspices of the LAMPS Working Group.
  </t>

</section>
 </back>
</rfc>
